<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Return of the Modular Adventure</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/</link>
        <description>Recent content on Return of the Modular Adventure</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 11:15:43 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Realism vs Verisimilitude</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/post/realism-vs-verisimilitude/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 11:15:43 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/post/realism-vs-verisimilitude/</guid>
        <description></description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>The Ruins of Riverguard Keep</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/ruins-of-riverguard-keep/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 08:06:12 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/ruins-of-riverguard-keep/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34; &gt;Back to the Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Enter the Strange</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/enter-the-strange/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 08:05:43 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/enter-the-strange/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34; &gt;Back to the Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Expedition: Rimemount</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/expedition-rimemount/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 08:05:26 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/expedition-rimemount/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34; &gt;Back to the Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>The Scarlet Halls of Blaithemoor Abbey</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/scarlet-halls/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 08:04:30 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/scarlet-halls/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34; &gt;Back to the Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Let&#39;s Talk About Session 0</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/post/session-0/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2022 10:55:31 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/post/session-0/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Article about Session 0!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>The Sewer-Smugglers Syndicate</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/sewer-smugglers-syndicate/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 12:34:45 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/sewer-smugglers-syndicate/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Sewer Smuggler&amp;rsquo;s Syndicate&lt;/strong&gt; - Written and Designed by C.J. DeLee &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Number of Characters:&lt;/strong&gt; 4-6 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Character Level:&lt;/strong&gt; 1-3 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34; &gt;Back to the Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction-for-players&#34;&gt;Introduction for Players&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city of Caerwyn is the bustling, river-side capitol of the magocracy of Alnor: the perfect place for a party of newly-anointed adventurers to prove their worth. Your party has been contracted by a powerful mage-priest: Lady Silra the Copper-Handed. The Lady Silra, known for her propensity of sponsoring new and brave adventurers, has asked you all to prove that you are worthy of her generosity by seeking out an associate of hers that has gone missing: Sir Aleks Drake. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
According to Lady Silra, Drake was sent to investigate rumors of illegal smuggling activity taking place somewhere in the sewers on the north edge of town. He left 3 days prior, and has not been seen since. It is up to you to descend into the sewers, find Drake, and put an end to any smuggling activity that may be taking place there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;information-for-gms&#34;&gt;Information for GMs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adventure is designed to be a small, introductory adventure for new players and GMs alike. If you are not used to a sandbox style of game play or using a modular approach when it comes to adventure modules, then this is the perfect place to start. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
This adventure will take you and your players through the sewers of Caerwyn, a vast network of corridors and passageways filled with all manner of creatures. This particular adventure will see your players through some maintenance tunnels, into a secret abandoned wizard&amp;rsquo;s laboratory, and into the den of the smugglers who have taken up residence in the north sewers of Caerwyn. This is a great adventure for low-level characters (levels 1-3). This can be used as just a one-shot, or it can be the introductory adventure in a whole new campaign set in the magocracy of Alnor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;download-the-adventure&#34;&gt;Download the Adventure&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/11WBzhagxFrVxa7ZL8idbRT9DLulgZWlG/preview&#34;
    width=&#34;370&#34; 
    height=&#34;480&#34;
    allow=&#34;autoplay&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.dmsguild.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Download for Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons 5th Edition (DM&amp;rsquo;s Guild)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.drivethrurpg.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Download for Pathfinder 2nd Edition (DriveThru RPG)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.drivethrurpg.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Download for Old-School Essentials and OSR Systems (DriveThru RPG)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34; &gt;Back to the Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Let&#39;s Build: A Dungeon</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/lets-build-a-dungeon/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 11:46:05 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/lets-build-a-dungeon/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When you are designing a new dungeon for an adventure to include in your campaign, I want you to ask yourself 3 questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is this place &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be used for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is this place &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; being used for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What was this placed used for before now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with just these 3 questions can really begin to flesh out the history of your dungeon, as well as provide you with ideas and inspiration that can be used when actually designing. For example, let&amp;rsquo;s build a sewer dungeon (that answers question number 1 for us already!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;question-1-what-is-this-place-supposed-to-be-used-for&#34;&gt;Question 1: What is this Place &lt;em&gt;Supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be Used for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is this place &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be used for? It&amp;rsquo;s a sewer system. We can expect dark, damp corridors with running, filthy water, grimy walls, and lots of rusted-shut iron doors blocking our way. Maybe there will be a few rooms designed for the sewer cleaners, stocked with cleaning instruments and lanterns. This question will drive the overall look and feel of the dungeon as this is what this place was built for to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure to make some notes on not just the &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; of the dungeon, but the &lt;em&gt;sounds&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;smells&lt;/em&gt; too! We have more than just one sense we use. As a GM, when it comes to describing your dungeon, you should always strive for using all 5 senses. You will most often use sight since that is the easiest to describe, but I challenge you to go further. What do the sewers smell like? What disgusting squelching sounds do the heroes hear as they traverse the sewage tunnels? What do the slimy, moss-covered walls feel like? The &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; challenging sense to describe is going to be taste; good luck including that one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;question-2-what-is-this-place-actually-being-used-for&#34;&gt;Question 2: What is this Place &lt;em&gt;Actually&lt;/em&gt; Being Used for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next question: What is this place &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; being used for? Now we are getting more complex. Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to introduce some &lt;em&gt;wild&lt;/em&gt; elements to answer this question. What else is going on in these sewers?? Are they being used by a group of smugglers to move contraband in and out of the city? Have a group of cultists set up a base of operations here so they may easily nab citizens from above for their sacrificial rituals? Has a deep rift formed here where horrors from the Underdark are now finding their way to the surface? Again, go wild!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;question-3-what-was-this-place-used-for-before-now&#34;&gt;Question 3: What was this Place Used for Before Now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where we will add in our third and final element to really cement and diversify our dungeon. This question asks who was here before? Or, more accurately: what was going on here that is no longer? In our sewer example, maybe some time ago, a powerful wizard or alchemist was using the sewers as a hidden lab. What would they have built down here? Some secret rooms hidden behind magical, illusory walls? Maybe they placed some magical rune traps that are still present, or maybe they constructed a golem to protect their lab that is still activated, wandering the sewage passages. This final element should clue your players into what strange and out-of-place sights they might find, and &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they are finding them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Search</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/search/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 13:15:21 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/search/</guid>
        <description></description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Archives</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/archives/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 13:14:33 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/archives/</guid>
        <description></description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Description or Dice</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/description-vs-dice/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 10:24:42 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/description-vs-dice/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Which of the following examples of play sounds better to you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Searching through the chest, you find 50 gold pieces and a vial of some mysterious liquid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rogue:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ll take the gold! Just gonna add it to the party funds&amp;hellip; Yep, definitely doing that right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; What&amp;rsquo;s the vial of liquid? * &lt;em&gt;rolls for Intelligence&lt;/em&gt; * Ah! I got a 19!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Well&amp;hellip; OK. It&amp;rsquo;s a very potent, magical acid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Sweet! Gonna store that away for a rainy day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Searching through the chest, you find 50 gold pieces and a vial of some mysterious liquid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rogue:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ll take the gold! Just gonna add it to the party funds&amp;hellip; Yep, definitely doing that right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; What&amp;rsquo;s the vial of liquid?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; You&amp;rsquo;re not sure. You&amp;rsquo;ve never seen this stuff before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Can I roll something to figure out what it is?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; No need to roll. Tell me, how would * &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; * figure out what it is?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Hmm. Well, what does the liquid look like, exactly?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; You hold the vial up to the torchlight and swirl it around. The liquid is a very dark grey, almost black, and appears to be quite viscous, sticking to the sides of the vial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; OK. I open it up and smell it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; It smells horribly acrid, burning your nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Alright, I think I have a hunch to what this stuff might be. Can I tip over just a drop onto a nearby piece of wood? Maybe the chest we found it in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Sure! As the single drop of the liquid hits the chest, it immediately begins to sizzle and smoke. It soon melts a hole clean through the chest and begins to melt into the stone beneath before burning out completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Ah! OK, very dangerous acid. Noted!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would prefer to run the game as the first example, then this post is not for you. I&amp;rsquo;m not saying there is anything objectively incorrect about playing any game following the sequence found in Example 1. We all enjoy the hobby in different ways, and that&amp;rsquo;s great! But this article is going to explore how we might get a bit more creative enjoyment out of the game by relying less on our character sheets and dice and more on our own creativity and imagination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;descriptions-or-dice-that-is-the-question&#34;&gt;Descriptions or Dice? That is the Question&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While playing TTRPGs, many, &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; things are seemingly meant to be resolved using dice and numbers on a character sheet. Want to hit the ogre with your sword? Roll for an attack. Trying to scale a sheer cliff? Roll an Athletics check. Bluffing your way past the guards into the palace? Roll a Deception check. These mechanics are designed to give us a way to determine an outcome for any given situation where there is the chance for failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all well and good, but this can quickly lead players to using their character sheets and the numbers as a crutch. Need to identify the magic potion you just found? Just roll some dice and get an answer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Adventures</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 09:09:37 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This page will host links to all adventures that people can read about and download to run in their campaigns. &lt;br&gt;


&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  You can view the entire archive of adventures &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34;&gt;here!&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sewer-smugglers-syndicate&#34;&gt;The Sewer-Smugglers Syndicate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A low-level, introductory dungeon for new players and GMs alike. Descend into the sewers and discover the secret lair of a smuggling syndicate. Can you put a stop to their evil deeds?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adventure is designed for 4-6 characters of levels 1-3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/sewer-smugglers-syndicate&#34; &gt;View Adventure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-ruins-of-riverguard-keep&#34;&gt;The Ruins of Riverguard Keep&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A low-level adventure set in the ruins of an ancient keep. 200 years ago, the Knights of the Ivory Leaf kept the lands surrounding the keep safe, but after their downfall, the keep&amp;rsquo;s ruins have become a hive of evil creatures that threaten the safety of the nearby villages. Will you brave the darkness of the Ruins of Riverguard Keep?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adventure is designed for 4-6 characters of levels 1-3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/ruins-of-riverguard-keep&#34; &gt;View Adventure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;enter-the-strange&#34;&gt;Enter the Strange&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year, the Festival of the Falling Stars draws hundreds from the villages of the countryside to the small town of Toren&amp;rsquo;s Field. Usually a time for celebration and merriment, this year, the festival takes a turn. When a wizard&amp;rsquo;s spell backfires, the entire town is uprooted, translocated across Existance to a distant realm of bizarre creatures and strange wilderness. Will you be able to save the town and bring everyone back home safely?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adventure is designed for 3-6 characters of levels 1-4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/enter-the-strange&#34; &gt;View Adventure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;expedition-rimemount&#34;&gt;Expedition: Rimemount&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rimemount: The Citadel of Frost. For hundreds of years, the inverted spire, dangling from the edge of a cliff above a frozen ravine, has claimed the lives of explorers and adventurers alike. Many claim the fortress to hold vast riches, forgotten after the fall of the Ice Giant Kings that ruled the land, though these are simply rumors&amp;hellip; Will you brave the frozen tundra to find if the rumors are true?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adventure is designed for 4-8 characters of levels 5-8&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/expedition-rimemount&#34; &gt;View Adventure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-scarlet-halls-of-blaithemoor-abbey&#34;&gt;The Scarlet Halls of Blaithemoor Abbey&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been a year since any have heard from the Lifeblood Monks of Blaithemoor Abbey. Multiple investigators have been sent to explore the abbey in an attempt to discern what has happened, but none have returned. You have been offered a generous sum to become the latest in a long line of agents who have ventured to the abbey. Will you discover the horrible secrets within, or will you simply become another of the lost and forgotten?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adventure is designed for 4-6 characters of levels 7-10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/scarlet-halls&#34; &gt;View Adventure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>About</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/about/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 09:06:01 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/about/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-brief-history-of-dungeons--dragons-adventures&#34;&gt;A Brief History of Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons Adventures&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/img/module-g1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Cover of module G1: Steading of the Hill Giant Chief&#34; style=&#34;float:right; height:450px; padding:15px&#34;


The first ever Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons adventure created and published by TSR was module &lt;strong&gt;G1: Steading of the Hill Giant Chief&lt;/strong&gt;. This would be the beginning of how adventures and campaigns were envisioned to be run by the creators of Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons: Small, &amp;ldquo;bite-sized&amp;rdquo; adventures, each taking characters through only a handful of character levels, that would be strung together to create a unique and enriched game experience. Every campaign was different, even if everyone was using the same published adventures. Depending on how you connected these adventures together would change the overall experience and story drastically. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Fast forward to 2014 and 5th Edition, and this modularity has all but evaporated. The first full adventure (excluding the Starter Set) published for 5e was &lt;strong&gt;Hoard of the Dragon Queen&lt;/strong&gt;, the first adventure in the Tyranny of Dragons set. This one adventure took characters from level 1 all the way through to level 7. Add on &lt;strong&gt;The Rise of Tiamat&lt;/strong&gt; and characters can be expected to reach level 15, a point when a lot of characters are retired. Across just 2 adventures, we have an entire campaign. For reference, the entire Against the Giants set of modules (3 adventures, G1, G2, and G3), were meant to take characters from level 8 to level 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-goal-of-return-of-the-modular-adventure&#34;&gt;The Goal of Return of the Modular Adventure&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where this website comes in. To me, the idea of having a large source of smaller, bite-sized adventures that are stitched together to form a more unique whole is FAR more interesting than running effectively the same evil dragon god campaign that everyone else is running. Sure, there can and will be some variation between tables that run Tyranny of Dragons, but only so much. At the end of the day, everyone will be fighting the dragon cults and killing Tiamat at the end. And this has become the standard for Wizards of the Coast and Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons. Here is a list of some of the 5e adventures with their listed level ranges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tyranny of Dragons (2 Adventures):&lt;/strong&gt; Levels 1-15&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Out of the Abyss (1 Adventure):&lt;/strong&gt; Levels 1-15&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Curse of Strahd (1 Adventure):&lt;/strong&gt; Levels 1-10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Waterdeep (2 Adventures):&lt;/strong&gt; Levels 1-20&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rime of the Frostmaiden (1 Adventure):&lt;/strong&gt; Levels 1-12&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An entire 5e campaign can be contained in just 2-3 adventures, sometimes 1! &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Now, I should say that &lt;strong&gt;none of this is bad by any means!&lt;/strong&gt; Many of the above listed adventures are FANTASTIC and you should definitely consider running them if they interest you! There is also nothing wrong with preferring this style of adventure module setup. The point I am trying to make is that the design philosophy for D&amp;amp;D adventures has changed. It&amp;rsquo;s not better or worse, just different. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Me, personally, I prefer to run a more unique, sandbox-y adventure. I would much rather have 10-20 different, smaller adventures that I can sprinkle throughout a world and set my players lose to discover them all. Not only would this be fun for me, but it would mean that I can use the same world AND the same adventures over and over again since there is no chance or guarantee that the players will play through all of the adventures I have seeded throughout the world. And that is what I am trying to do with this site. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
My plan is to create and release adventure modules with the design ideology of classic TSR in mind: bite-sized adventures that can be mixed and matched to create unique and engaging campaigns. I also will be taking my experiences as a GM and writing articles in the hopes to help new GMs learn some of the ropes, and to present some new ways of thinking when it comes to running the game. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
You can check out the current roster of adventures &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures&#34; &gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and read up on some of my GM tips and thoughts &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/archives&#34; &gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Thanks for reading, and enjoy the adventure! &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
~ C.J. DeLee&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>The Problem with Puzzles</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/post/problem-with-puzzles/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 13:52:03 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/post/problem-with-puzzles/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s set the scene: You have been preparing your next game session &lt;em&gt;for weeks&lt;/em&gt; now and it is complete. The party is getting ready to dive head first into an evil mage&amp;rsquo;s lair to put a stop to their nefarious plot before it&amp;rsquo;s too late. You&amp;rsquo;ve mapped the dungeon, placed the traps and treasure, stocked your wandering monster and encounter tables, and built out just about every single thing you could think of. And, the &lt;em&gt;piece de resistance&lt;/em&gt;: a beautifully devious and challenging puzzle to mess with your players&amp;rsquo; brains. It is the PERFECT set piece for your big bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to game night, and everything falls apart. Why? The entire 4 hour session is spent with the players banging their heads against a wall ceaselessly trying to piece together your masterful puzzle. They can&amp;rsquo;t figure it out, so they&amp;rsquo;re mad, and you think that the puzzle should have been solved &lt;strong&gt;hours&lt;/strong&gt; ago, so now you&amp;rsquo;re mad too! At the end of the night, everyone goes home unsatisfied. Try again next week, I suppose?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-do-we-want-puzzles&#34;&gt;Why Do We &lt;em&gt;Want&lt;/em&gt; Puzzles?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every single GM at some point in their career has thought to themselves: &amp;ldquo;Ooooh, this would be the &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; time to include a nice, fun puzzle!&amp;rdquo;. And that&amp;rsquo;s perfectly valid! I&amp;rsquo;ve had the same thoughts and desires in the past. We want to challenge our players in a new way. Sure, we can throw some monsters or a trap at them, but those are simply tools to deplete resources before the big encounter at the end of the adventure. A puzzle, on the other hand, gives us the chance to challenge our players &lt;em&gt;minds&lt;/em&gt; instead of their character sheets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel it is also more often than not that the situation outline above happens: we think of a great puzzle that&amp;rsquo;s not &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; challenging, but just challenging enough to be satisfying, and the players &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; can&amp;rsquo;t figure it out to save their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-you-need-puzzles&#34;&gt;Do You &lt;em&gt;Need&lt;/em&gt; Puzzles?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short answer is no. You don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to include puzzles in your dungeons to have a fulfilling game experience. You could run an entire multi-year campaign without a single puzzle and it could still be the best game you&amp;rsquo;ve ever run. As with almost every aspect of this hobby, it&amp;rsquo;s up to you and your players what bits and pieces you use. If puzzles don&amp;rsquo;t fit the game you are running, don&amp;rsquo;t use &amp;rsquo;em! A good way to know if puzzles will work with your campaign is to get some &lt;strong&gt;player buy-in&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;player-buy-in&#34;&gt;Player Buy-In&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something that should be brought up during a session 0 (check out my thoughts on session 0&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/post/session-0&#34; &gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!) When discussing the campaign you are wanting to run, you should bring up puzzles. Ask your players what their thoughts are, if they would even like puzzles, how often to include puzzles, and how challenging they should be. If you have a group of players that want a lot of &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; challenging puzzles thrown their way, &lt;strong&gt;AND&lt;/strong&gt; you&amp;rsquo;re happy with running that kind of game, then that is something you should know before you start working on the bulk of the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-make-puzzles-work&#34;&gt;How to Make Puzzles Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so you&amp;rsquo;ve decided that you do want puzzles in your game. That&amp;rsquo;s great! We&amp;rsquo;re going to go through how I think puzzles can be added to a game effectively. As we already determined, puzzles need to be easy enough that the players aren&amp;rsquo;t banging their heads against the wall trying to figure it out, but challenging enough to be satisfying. Again, you will want to first make sure your players will get some enjoyment out of solving puzzles before you start littering your campaign with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;start-at-the-end&#34;&gt;Start at the End&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;ve established that your players actually &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; puzzles, we can actually start building one. The best advice I can give here is to start at the end. What is the solution, the end result? Where do you want your players &lt;em&gt;to end up&lt;/em&gt; after solving the puzzle? The solution to the puzzle is the most important piece. Once the puzzle is solved, what&amp;rsquo;s going to happen? Is a secret passage going to open up? Or will the players learn some new, important information that will help them later? Does solving the puzzle open an inter-dimensional gate, set free an evil necromancer&amp;rsquo;s prisoner, or does it simply open the way to a treasure horde?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing where you&amp;rsquo;re players will end up will help to inform you on how they get there. It can also become a great source of inspiration. Knowing what the puzzle is protecting can inform on how someone would have built the puzzle in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;build-your-pieces-with-an-asterisk&#34;&gt;Build Your Pieces (with an Asterisk)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you know where you are going, you can start to figure out how your players will get there. This is what most people think of when imagining designing a puzzle for their players. It&amp;rsquo;s also the most fun part! This is where you can get &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; creative with your puzzles. What buttons need to be pressed to make the thing do the other thing? That&amp;rsquo;s what we get to create!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re anything like me as a GM, one of your first worries will be &amp;ldquo;How can I make this puzzle realistic?&amp;rdquo; In reality, you can&amp;rsquo;t. The real world doesn&amp;rsquo;t really operate on Indiana Jones rules when it comes to puzzles. But that&amp;rsquo;s OK, because we don&amp;rsquo;t need to worry about &lt;em&gt;realism&lt;/em&gt;. All we need to worry about is &lt;em&gt;verisimilitude&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/post/realism-vs-verisimilitude&#34; &gt;Realism vs. Verisimilitude&lt;/a&gt;). Our puzzle doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to be realistic, just believable. If our players &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; that this puzzle &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; exist in this world, then we&amp;rsquo;ve succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;clue-them-in&#34;&gt;Clue Them In&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
