<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Return of the Modular Adventure</title>
        <link>http://example.org/</link>
        <description>Recent content on Return of the Modular Adventure</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 12:34:45 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://example.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>The Sewer-Smugglers Syndicate</title>
        <link>http://example.org/adventures-archive/sewer-smugglers-syndicate/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 12:34:45 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://example.org/adventures-archive/sewer-smugglers-syndicate/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;object data=&#34;/pdf/isometric-paper.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700px&#34; height=&#34;700px&#34;&gt;
&lt;embed src=&#34;http://example.org/pdf/isometric-paper.pdf&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This browser does not support PDFs. Please download the PDF to view it: &lt;a href=&#34;http://example.org/pdf/isometric-paper.pdf&#34;&gt;Download PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/embed&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;


</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Let&#39;s Build: A Dungeon</title>
        <link>http://example.org/lets-build-a-dungeon/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 11:46:05 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://example.org/lets-build-a-dungeon/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When you are designing a new dungeon for an adventure to include in your campaign, I want you to ask yourself 3 questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is this place &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be used for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is this place &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; being used for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What was this placed used for before now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with just these 3 questions can really begin to flesh out the history of your dungeon, as well as provide you with ideas and inspiration that can be used when actually designing. For example, let&amp;rsquo;s build a sewer dungeon (that answers question number 1 for us already!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;question-1-what-is-this-place-supposed-to-be-used-for&#34;&gt;Question 1: What is this Place &lt;em&gt;Supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be Used for?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is this place &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be used for? It&amp;rsquo;s a sewer system. We can expect dark, damp corridors with running, filthy water, grimy walls, and lots of rusted-shut iron doors blocking our way. Maybe there will be a few rooms designed for the sewer cleaners, stocked with cleaning instruments and lanterns. This question will drive the overall look and feel of the dungeon as this is what this place was built for to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure to make some notes on not just the &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; of the dungeon, but the &lt;em&gt;sounds&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;smells&lt;/em&gt; too! We have more than just one sense we use. As a GM, when it comes to describing your dungeon, you should always strive for using all 5 senses. You will most often use sight since that is the easiest to describe, but I challenge you to go further. What do the sewers smell like? What disgusting squelching sounds do the heroes hear as they traverse the sewage tunnels? What do the slimy, moss-covered walls feel like? The &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; challenging sense to describe is going to be taste; good luck including that one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;question-2-what-is-this-place-actually-being-used-for&#34;&gt;Question 2: What is this Place &lt;em&gt;Actually&lt;/em&gt; Being Used for?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next question: What is this place &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; being used for? Now we are getting more complex. Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to introduce some &lt;em&gt;wild&lt;/em&gt; elements to answer this question. What else is going on in these sewers?? Are they being used by a group of smugglers to move contraband in and out of the city? Have a group of cultists set up a base of operations here so they may easily nab citizens from above for their sacrificial rituals? Has a deep rift formed here where horrors from the Underdark are now finding their way to the surface? Again, go wild!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;question-3-what-was-this-place-used-for-before-now&#34;&gt;Question 3: What was this Place Used for Before Now?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where we will add in our third and final element to really cement and diversify our dungeon. This question asks who was here before? Or, more accurately: what was going on here that is no longer? In our sewer example, maybe some time ago, a powerful wizard or alchemist was using the sewers as a hidden lab. What would they have built down here? Some secret rooms hidden behind magical, illusory walls? Maybe they placed some magical rune traps that are still present, or maybe they constructed a golem to protect their lab that is still activated, wandering the sewage passages. This final element should clue your players into what strange and out-of-place sights they might find, and &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they are finding them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Search</title>
        <link>http://example.org/search/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 13:15:21 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://example.org/search/</guid>
        <description></description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Archives</title>
        <link>http://example.org/archives/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 13:14:33 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://example.org/archives/</guid>
        <description></description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Description or Dice</title>
        <link>http://example.org/description-vs-dice/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 10:24:42 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://example.org/description-vs-dice/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Which of the following examples of play sounds better to you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Searching through the chest, you find 50 gold pieces and a vial of some mysterious liquid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rogue:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ll take the gold! Just gonna add it to the party funds&amp;hellip; Yep, definitely doing that right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; What&amp;rsquo;s the vial of liquid? * &lt;em&gt;rolls for Intelligence&lt;/em&gt; * Ah! I got a 19!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Well&amp;hellip; OK. It&amp;rsquo;s a very potent, magical acid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Sweet! Gonna store that away for a rainy day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Searching through the chest, you find 50 gold pieces and a vial of some mysterious liquid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rogue:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ll take the gold! Just gonna add it to the party funds&amp;hellip; Yep, definitely doing that right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; What&amp;rsquo;s the vial of liquid?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; You&amp;rsquo;re not sure. You&amp;rsquo;ve never seen this stuff before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Can I roll something to figure out what it is?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; No need to roll. Tell me, how would * &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; * figure out what it is?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Hmm. Well, what does the liquid look like, exactly?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; You hold the vial up to the torchlight and swirl it around. The liquid is a very dark grey, almost black, and appears to be quite viscous, sticking to the sides of the vial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; OK. I open it up and smell it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; It smells horribly acrid, burning your nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Alright, I think I have a hunch to what this stuff might be. Can I tip over just a drop onto a nearby piece of wood? Maybe the chest we found it in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Sure! As the single drop of the liquid hits the chest, it immediately begins to sizzle and smoke. It soon melts a hole clean through the chest and begins to melt into the stone beneath before burning out completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Ah! OK, very dangerous acid. Noted!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would prefer to run the game as the first example, then this post is not for you. I&amp;rsquo;m not saying there is anything objectively incorrect about playing any game following the sequence found in Example 1. We all enjoy the hobby in different ways, and that&amp;rsquo;s great! But this article is going to explore how we might get a bit more creative enjoyment out of the game by relying less on our character sheets and dice and more on our own creativity and imagination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;descriptions-or-dice-that-is-the-question&#34;&gt;Descriptions or Dice? That is the Question&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While playing TTRPGs, many, &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; things are seemingly meant to be resolved using dice and numbers on a character sheet. Want to hit the ogre with your sword? Roll for an attack. Trying to scale a sheer cliff? Roll an Athletics check. Bluffing your way past the guards into the palace? Roll a Deception check. These mechanics are designed to give us a way to determine an outcome for any given situation where there is the chance for failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all well and good, but this can quickly lead players to using their character sheets and the numbers as a crutch. Need to identify the magic potion you just found? Just roll some dice and get an answer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Adventures</title>
        <link>http://example.org/adventures/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 09:09:37 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://example.org/adventures/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This page will host links to all adventures that people can read about and download to run in their campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-sewer-smugglers-syndicate&#34;&gt;The Sewer-Smugglers Syndicate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where Adventure 1 will go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://example.org/adventures-archive/sewer-smugglers-syndicate&#34; &gt;View Adventure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;adventure-2&#34;&gt;Adventure 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where Adventure 2 will go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;adventure-3&#34;&gt;Adventure 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where Adventure 3 will go.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>About</title>
        <link>http://example.org/about/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 09:06:01 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://example.org/about/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-return-of-the-modular-adventure&#34;&gt;About Return of the Modular Adventure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where I will put all of the about information. What is a &amp;ldquo;modular adventure&amp;rdquo;? How does it work? Why should I do this?What else can I find on this site?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>The Problem with Puzzles</title>
        <link>http://example.org/post/problem-with-puzzles/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 13:52:03 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://example.org/post/problem-with-puzzles/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s set the scene: You have been preparing your next game session &lt;em&gt;for weeks&lt;/em&gt; now and it is complete. The party is getting ready to dive head first into an evil mage&amp;rsquo;s lair to put a stop to their nefarious plot before it&amp;rsquo;s too late. You&amp;rsquo;ve mapped the dungeon, placed the traps and treasure, stocked your wandering monster and encounter tables, and built out just about every single thing you could think of. And, the &lt;em&gt;piece de resistance&lt;/em&gt;: a beautifully devious and challenging puzzle to mess with your players&amp;rsquo; brains. It is the PERFECT set piece for your big bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to game night, and everything falls apart. Why? The entire 4 hour session is spent with the players banging their heads against a wall ceaslessly trying to piece together your masterful puzzle. They can&amp;rsquo;t figure it out, so they&amp;rsquo;re mad, and you think that the puzzle should have been solved &lt;strong&gt;hours&lt;/strong&gt; ago, so now you&amp;rsquo;re mad too! At the end of the night, everyone goes home unsatisfied. Try again next week, I suppose?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-do-we-want-puzzles&#34;&gt;Why Do We &lt;em&gt;Want&lt;/em&gt; Puzzles?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every single GM at some point in their career has thought to themselves: &amp;ldquo;Ooooh, this would be the &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; time to include a nice, fun puzzle!&amp;rdquo;. And that&amp;rsquo;s perfectly valid! I&amp;rsquo;ve had the same thoughts and desires in the past. We want to challenge our players in a new way. Sure, we can throw some monsters or a trap at them, but those are simply tools to deplete resources before the big encounter at the end of the adventure. A puzzle, on the other hand, gives us the chance to challenge our players &lt;em&gt;minds&lt;/em&gt; instead of their character sheets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel it is also more often than not that the situation outline above happens: we think of a great puzzle that&amp;rsquo;s not &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; challenging, but just challenging enough to be satisfying, and the players &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; can&amp;rsquo;t figure it out to save their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;do-you-need-puzzles&#34;&gt;Do You &lt;em&gt;Need&lt;/em&gt; Puzzles?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-make-puzzles-work&#34;&gt;How to Make Puzzles Work&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
