<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Players on Return of the Modular Adventure</title>
        <link>http://example.org/tags/players/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Players on Return of the Modular Adventure</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 10:24:42 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://example.org/tags/players/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Description or Dice</title>
        <link>http://example.org/description-vs-dice/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 10:24:42 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://example.org/description-vs-dice/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Which of the following examples of play sounds better to you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Searching through the chest, you find 50 gold pieces and a vial of some mysterious liquid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rogue:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ll take the gold! Just gonna add it to the party funds&amp;hellip; Yep, definitely doing that right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; What&amp;rsquo;s the vial of liquid? * &lt;em&gt;rolls for Intelligence&lt;/em&gt; * Ah! I got a 19!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Well&amp;hellip; OK. It&amp;rsquo;s a very potent, magical acid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Sweet! Gonna store that away for a rainy day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Searching through the chest, you find 50 gold pieces and a vial of some mysterious liquid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rogue:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ll take the gold! Just gonna add it to the party funds&amp;hellip; Yep, definitely doing that right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; What&amp;rsquo;s the vial of liquid?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; You&amp;rsquo;re not sure. You&amp;rsquo;ve never seen this stuff before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Can I roll something to figure out what it is?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; No need to roll. Tell me, how would * &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; * figure out what it is?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Hmm. Well, what does the liquid look like, exactly?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; You hold the vial up to the torchlight and swirl it around. The liquid is a very dark grey, almost black, and appears to be quite viscous, sticking to the sides of the vial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; OK. I open it up and smell it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; It smells horribly acrid, burning your nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Alright, I think I have a hunch to what this stuff might be. Can I tip over just a drop onto a nearby piece of wood? Maybe the chest we found it in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Sure! As the single drop of the liquid hits the chest, it immediately begins to sizzle and smoke. It soon melts a hole clean through the chest and begins to melt into the stone beneath before burning out completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;     &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Ah! OK, very dangerous acid. Noted!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would prefer to run the game as the first example, then this post is not for you. I&amp;rsquo;m not saying there is anything objectively incorrect about playing any game following the sequence found in Example 1. We all enjoy the hobby in different ways, and that&amp;rsquo;s great! But this article is going to explore how we might get a bit more creative enjoyment out of the game by relying less on our character sheets and dice and more on our own creativity and imagination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;descriptions-or-dice-that-is-the-question&#34;&gt;Descriptions or Dice? That is the Question&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While playing TTRPGs, many, &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; things are seemingly meant to be resolved using dice and numbers on a character sheet. Want to hit the ogre with your sword? Roll for an attack. Trying to scale a sheer cliff? Roll an Athletics check. Bluffing your way past the guards into the palace? Roll a Deception check. These mechanics are designed to give us a way to determine an outcome for any given situation where there is the chance for failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all well and good, but this can quickly lead players to using their character sheets and the numbers as a crutch. Need to identify the magic potion you just found? Just roll some dice and get an answer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
