<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Adventure on Return of the Modular Adventure</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/categories/adventure/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Adventure on Return of the Modular Adventure</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 08:06:12 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/categories/adventure/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>The Ruins of Riverguard Keep</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/ruins-of-riverguard-keep/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 08:06:12 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/ruins-of-riverguard-keep/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34; &gt;Back to the Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Enter the Strange</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/enter-the-strange/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 08:05:43 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/enter-the-strange/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34; &gt;Back to the Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Expedition: Rimemount</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/expedition-rimemount/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 08:05:26 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/expedition-rimemount/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34; &gt;Back to the Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>The Scarlet Halls of Blaithemoor Abbey</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/scarlet-halls/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 08:04:30 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/scarlet-halls/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34; &gt;Back to the Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>The Sewer-Smugglers Syndicate</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/sewer-smugglers-syndicate/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 12:34:45 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive/sewer-smugglers-syndicate/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Sewer Smuggler&amp;rsquo;s Syndicate&lt;/strong&gt; - Written and Designed by C.J. DeLee &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Number of Characters:&lt;/strong&gt; 4-6 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Character Level:&lt;/strong&gt; 1-3 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34; &gt;Back to the Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction-for-players&#34;&gt;Introduction for Players&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city of Caerwyn is the bustling, river-side capitol of the magocracy of Alnor: the perfect place for a party of newly-anointed adventurers to prove their worth. Your party has been contracted by a powerful mage-priest: Lady Silra the Copper-Handed. The Lady Silra, known for her propensity of sponsoring new and brave adventurers, has asked you all to prove that you are worthy of her generosity by seeking out an associate of hers that has gone missing: Sir Aleks Drake. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
According to Lady Silra, Drake was sent to investigate rumors of illegal smuggling activity taking place somewhere in the sewers on the north edge of town. He left 3 days prior, and has not been seen since. It is up to you to descend into the sewers, find Drake, and put an end to any smuggling activity that may be taking place there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;information-for-gms&#34;&gt;Information for GMs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adventure is designed to be a small, introductory adventure for new players and GMs alike. If you are not used to a sandbox style of game play or using a modular approach when it comes to adventure modules, then this is the perfect place to start. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
This adventure will take you and your players through the sewers of Caerwyn, a vast network of corridors and passageways filled with all manner of creatures. This particular adventure will see your players through some maintenance tunnels, into a secret abandoned wizard&amp;rsquo;s laboratory, and into the den of the smugglers who have taken up residence in the north sewers of Caerwyn. This is a great adventure for low-level characters (levels 1-3). This can be used as just a one-shot, or it can be the introductory adventure in a whole new campaign set in the magocracy of Alnor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;download-the-adventure&#34;&gt;Download the Adventure&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/11WBzhagxFrVxa7ZL8idbRT9DLulgZWlG/preview&#34;
    width=&#34;370&#34; 
    height=&#34;480&#34;
    allow=&#34;autoplay&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.dmsguild.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Download for Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons 5th Edition (DM&amp;rsquo;s Guild)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.drivethrurpg.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Download for Pathfinder 2nd Edition (DriveThru RPG)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.drivethrurpg.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Download for Old-School Essentials and OSR Systems (DriveThru RPG)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/adventures-archive&#34; &gt;Back to the Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Let&#39;s Build: A Dungeon</title>
        <link>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/lets-build-a-dungeon/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 11:46:05 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://www.returnofthemodularadventure.com/lets-build-a-dungeon/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When you are designing a new dungeon for an adventure to include in your campaign, I want you to ask yourself 3 questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is this place &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be used for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is this place &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; being used for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What was this placed used for before now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with just these 3 questions can really begin to flesh out the history of your dungeon, as well as provide you with ideas and inspiration that can be used when actually designing. For example, let&amp;rsquo;s build a sewer dungeon (that answers question number 1 for us already!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;question-1-what-is-this-place-supposed-to-be-used-for&#34;&gt;Question 1: What is this Place &lt;em&gt;Supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be Used for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is this place &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be used for? It&amp;rsquo;s a sewer system. We can expect dark, damp corridors with running, filthy water, grimy walls, and lots of rusted-shut iron doors blocking our way. Maybe there will be a few rooms designed for the sewer cleaners, stocked with cleaning instruments and lanterns. This question will drive the overall look and feel of the dungeon as this is what this place was built for to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure to make some notes on not just the &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; of the dungeon, but the &lt;em&gt;sounds&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;smells&lt;/em&gt; too! We have more than just one sense we use. As a GM, when it comes to describing your dungeon, you should always strive for using all 5 senses. You will most often use sight since that is the easiest to describe, but I challenge you to go further. What do the sewers smell like? What disgusting squelching sounds do the heroes hear as they traverse the sewage tunnels? What do the slimy, moss-covered walls feel like? The &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; challenging sense to describe is going to be taste; good luck including that one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;question-2-what-is-this-place-actually-being-used-for&#34;&gt;Question 2: What is this Place &lt;em&gt;Actually&lt;/em&gt; Being Used for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next question: What is this place &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; being used for? Now we are getting more complex. Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to introduce some &lt;em&gt;wild&lt;/em&gt; elements to answer this question. What else is going on in these sewers?? Are they being used by a group of smugglers to move contraband in and out of the city? Have a group of cultists set up a base of operations here so they may easily nab citizens from above for their sacrificial rituals? Has a deep rift formed here where horrors from the Underdark are now finding their way to the surface? Again, go wild!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;question-3-what-was-this-place-used-for-before-now&#34;&gt;Question 3: What was this Place Used for Before Now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where we will add in our third and final element to really cement and diversify our dungeon. This question asks who was here before? Or, more accurately: what was going on here that is no longer? In our sewer example, maybe some time ago, a powerful wizard or alchemist was using the sewers as a hidden lab. What would they have built down here? Some secret rooms hidden behind magical, illusory walls? Maybe they placed some magical rune traps that are still present, or maybe they constructed a golem to protect their lab that is still activated, wandering the sewage passages. This final element should clue your players into what strange and out-of-place sights they might find, and &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they are finding them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
